Jerome E. Moberg Papers
Jerome E. Moberg Papers
1915-1993
1935-1975
Moberg, Jerome E. (Jerome Emanuel), 1913-1993.
50 linear ft.
Papers of the American industrial designer (primarily of cutlery, bathroom fixtures and accessories, and toy airplanes). Collection includes correspondence and client files, drawings, product brochures, metal castings, and wood, metal, or plastic product samples of household knives, tableware, carving sets, and bathroom accessories. Also, personal memorabilia.
149756
Biographical History
Jerome E. Moberg (1913-1992) was an American industrial designer. Born in Jamestown, New York, the son of a metal worker, "Jerry" Moberg attended Alfred University, the University of Chicago, and Lawrence Technical College in Detroit. Winner of four Good Design Awards, he designed hundreds of commercial products, working primarily for Robeson Cutlery Company in Perry, New York. His cutlery work, which won numerous prizes, included household knives, tableware, hunting knives, and carving sets; it was exhibited at the Brussells Worlds Fair in 1958 and today is represented in museums in Boston, Chicago, and New York. In later years he also designed for Bush Brothers Inc., creating plastic and light metal bathroom fixtures for Sears and for motel chains.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jerome E. Moberg Papers has received only preliminary processing. The collection contains business records; personal papers, memorabilia, design publications, and advertising clipping files; and metal castings and various wooden, metal, or plastic product samples.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received only preliminary processing and remains in the original folders and original order. Business records are alphabetical by client, job, or subject, as received.
Related Material
has the papers of many important industrial designers, including Lurelle Guild, Arthur Pulos, Budd Steinhilber, Walter Dorwin Teague, John Vassos, and Russel Wright. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Industrial Design; Moberg, Jerome E. (Jerome Emanuel), 1913-1993.; Cutlery -- Design and construction.; Industrial design.; Industrial designers -- United States.; Interior decoration accessories -- Design and construction.; Kitchen utensils -- Design and construction.; Knives -- Design and construction.; Toys -- Design and construction.; Castings.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Memorabilia.; Notebooks.; Samples.; Industrial designers.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Jerome E. Moberg.
Inventory
- Business records
  - AAMA - Bush Brothers (Box 1)
  - Bush Brothers - Cutlery (Box 2)
  - Cutting boards - Hume, Clement, Hume and Lee (Box 3)
  - Ideas - Memcee (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous - Quotations (Box 5)
  - Resumes - Samples (Box 6)
  - Samples, circa 1960s-1970s; industrial printed material (Box 7)
  - Scale modeling - Wyandotte Toys (Box 8)
- Personal papers
  - Aetna - Laura (biographical information) (Box 9)
  - M & T Brokerage - Utilities (Box 10)
  - Design and industrial publications (Box 11)
  - Advertising clipping file (Box 11)
  - Notebooks (Box 12)
  - Address file (Box 12)
  - Print blocks (Box 12)
  - Memorabilia, tie clips, lighter, watches, pins, seal imprinter, paperweight, scissors, cufflinks (Box 12)
- Models and product samples
  - Bush Bros. plastic samples, hamper and bathroom fixtures (Oversize 31)
  - Cooking utensils and pellet gun barrell (Oversize 3)
  - Cutlery boards (wood), various (Box 14)
  - Cutlery board and storage boxes (Robeson) (Box 15)
  - Cutlery, plastic and wooden handled models (Box 19)
  - Cutlery and utensils (Box 18)
  - Metal castings and models (Box 13)
  - Metal and glass fixture parts and samples (Box 16)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Oversize 1)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Oversize 2)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Oversize 32)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Oversize 33)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Oversize 34)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Box 20)
  - Molded plastic samples, shutters, molding, edging, decorative panels, a few unidentifiable items (Box 21)
- Technical drawings, artwork, and miscellany
  - Aircraft designs, 1930s (Oversize 10)
  - Aircraft designs, 1930s (Oversize 11)
  - Bush Bros. papers and drawings (Box 17)
  - Bush Bros. product designs and patent applications (Oversize 5)
  - Drafting table drawing arm (Oversize 4)
  - Early designs, 1930s-1940s (Oversize 9)
  - Maps (Oversize 12)
  - Personal memorabilia, juvenilia, family (Oversize 8)
  - Robeson Cutlery drawings, 1957-1963 (Map-case 139)
  - Robeson Cutlery drawings, 1957-1963 (Map-case 140)
  - Robeson printed samples, ads, artwork, 1950s-1960s (Oversize 6)
  - Student artwork and early designs, undated (Oversize 7)
  - Technical drawings and artwork, 1930s-1940s (Oversize 14)
  - Technical drawings, 1930s-1940s (Oversize 15)
  - Technical drawings, 1930s-1940s (Oversize 16)
  - Technical drawings, 1960s (Oversize 17)
  - Technical drawings, Auburn College, 1960s (Oversize 18)
  - Technical drawings, 1970s (Oversize 19)
  - Technical drawings, 1970-1972 (Oversize 20)
  - Technical drawings, 1970-1972 (Oversize 21)
  - Technical drawings, 1973 (Oversize 22)
  - Technical drawings, 1974-1975 (Oversize 23)
  - Technical drawings, 1974-1975 (Oversize 24)
  - Technical drawings, 1976 (Oversize 25)
  - Technical drawings, 1977; 1979 (Oversize 26)
  - Technical drawings, 1980-1983 (Oversize 27)
  - Technical drawings, Auburn College, 1960s (Oversize 28)
  - Unidentified artwork, undated (Oversize 13)